<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iust reward of rebels, or The life and death of Iack Straw, and Wat Tyler, who for their rebellion and disobedience to ther king and country, were suddenly slaine, and all their tumultuous rout covercome and put to flight. Whereunto is added the ghost of Iack Straw, as he lately appeared to the rebells in Ireland, wishing them to forbeare and repent of their divellish and inhumane actions against their lawfull King and country.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E136_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866797</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866797</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156461</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156461)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 24:E136[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iust reward of rebels, or The life and death of Iack Straw, and Wat Tyler, who for their rebellion and disobedience to ther king and country, were suddenly slaine, and all their tumultuous rout covercome and put to flight. Whereunto is added the ghost of Iack Straw, as he lately appeared to the rebells in Ireland, wishing them to forbeare and repent of their divellish and inhumane actions against their lawfull King and country.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for F. Couls, I. Wright, T. Banks and T. Bates,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>With title page woodcut, other ill.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Straw, Jack, d. 1381? --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tyler, Wat, d. 1381 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Richard II, 1377-1399 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:156461:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> The iuſt reward of Rebels, OR The Life and Death of <hi>Iack Straw,</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> who for their Rebellion and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to their King and Country, were ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſlaine, and all their tumultuous Rout overcome and put to flight.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added the Ghoſt of <hi>Iack Straw,</hi> as he lately appeared to the Rebells in Ireland, wiſhing them to forbeare and repent of their Divelliſh and inhumane Actions againſt their lawfull King and Country.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>a skeleton and formally dressed man dance in a circle of four robed priests</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>F. Couls, I. Wright, T. Banks</hi> and <hi>T. Bates.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Wat Tyler and Jack Straw" type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:156461:2"/>
            <head>The Rebellious Life and Death of VVat Tyler and Iack Straw.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Bedience (ſaith a learned Father) is a Vertue due both unto God and man, to God as our Creator, to Man as our ſuperiour; and a learned Philoſopher tells us, that to know how to obey, and how to command are two things and thus differ; for the one commeth by Nature, the other by Experience: That Country is well manag'd where the King knoweth Royalty to governe, and his People faithfully to ſerve. The Prince is ſupreame head of all Authority, and the Subject is injoyn'd to obey God, the Lawes, and his Prince; for Treaſon can have no place where Obedience claimeth principality. So much for the Introduction, I come now to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond of that name, the Son of Prince
<hi>Edward,</hi> (commonly cald the black Prince) the eldeſt Son of King
<hi>Edward</hi> the third, being then a Child of the age of eleaven yeares, began his Raigne over the Realme of England the 22. of <hi>Iune,</hi> in the yeare of our Redemption 1327. being the 13. yeare of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſixt of that name, then King of <hi>France,</hi> he was cald <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Burdeux</hi> as being borne there, and upon the fifteenth day of
<hi>Iuly</hi> in the yeare above mentioned, was Crowned at Weſtminſter, being the day of the tranſlation of St. <hi>Swithin,</hi> which time was Major <hi>Nicholas Brembre</hi> Grocer, and <hi>Andrew Pikman</hi> and
<hi>Nicholas Twifford</hi> Shreifes.</p>
            <p>In the third yeare of this Kings Raigne, and toward the latter end thereof, <hi>William Walworth</hi> Fiſhmonger being Major, and <hi>Walter Docket,</hi> and <hi>William Knighthood</hi> Shriefes. About the beginning of ſummer in divers places of the Land, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aroſe in <hi>Kent,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> in <hi>Suffolk</hi> &amp;c. and made amongſt them Rulers and Captaines, of which (according to ſome Chronologers) one was named
<hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> a ſecond <hi>William Waw,</hi> a third <hi>Iack Straw,</hi> a fourth <hi>Iack Shepheard,</hi> a fifth <hi>Tom Miller,</hi> a ſixt <hi>Hob Carter,</hi> but the beſt and moſt approved Records ſtile them thus: <pb facs="tcp:156461:2"/> 
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> or <hi>Walter Tylor, Iohn,</hi> or
<hi>Iack Straw, Iohn Kerby, Allen Threader, Thomas Skot,</hi> and <hi>Ralph Rugg,</hi> all of them of that diſſolute and deſperate condition, that like <hi>Heroſtratus,</hi> who ſet fire of <hi>Dianaes</hi> Temple in
<hi>Epheſus</hi> (which was one of the ſeaven wonders of the world) and burnt it downe to the ground for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but that he would be talked of after his death, according to the ſtrict decree of of the
<hi>Epheſians,</hi> (who made it death for ony man to ſpeake of her) are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee named.</p>
            <p>But I proceed in my Diſcourſe, according to the moſt exact and authentick Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle of St. <hi>Albones,</hi> which makes this report. The young King in his minor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty granted a great Taxe upon his Subjects both ſpirituall and temporall, which was called Pole-mony, that is a groat upon every pole or head, which could call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves man or woman: which comming in very ſlowly, divers Courtiers about the King deſirous to enrich themſelves by the goods of the Commons, complained that it was not faithfully gathered by the Collectors, wherefore they offered to pay a great ſumme of mony to farme it of the King, which they would gather over and above that which had bin paid, ſo that by the King they might bee ſufficiently au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed, who getting Letters to that purpoſe, ſate as Commiſſioners in divers places of <hi>Kent,</hi> and
<hi>Eſſex,</hi> and handled the people very roughly and diſcourteouſly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond either mercy or conſcience, who no doubt if they had proceeded with cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and humanity, might have prevented thoſe fearefull and horrible diſaſters which after hapned, for the Commons tooke counſell, and they had private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions amongſt themſelves and growing to an head made reſiſtance againſt thoſe exactors riſing againſt them, of which ſome they ſlew, others dangerouſly woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the reſt were forced to ſave themſelves by flight.</p>
            <p>Which tumult began firſt in <hi>Kent,</hi> and upon this occaſion following one of thoſe Collectors of the Groates or Pole-mony, comming to the houſe of one <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> (ſo called becauſe he was of that Trade, for his ſir name is not otherwiſe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred) who dwelt at
<hi>Dartford</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> twelve miles from <hi>London)</hi> and demanded of his wife mony for her Husband, her ſelfe, and her ſervant, which ſhe refuſed not to pay, but the covetous greedy fellow ſeeing her daughter, a maid ſcarſe 15. yeares of age in the houſe, demanded a groat for her alſo: to whom ſhe modeſtly replyed, that ſhe was but a child, and was not arrived unto that mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rity to be reckoned in the number of women: No, ſaith the Collector, that ſhall be tryed, and taking her up in his armes moſt uncivilly and diſhoneſtly tooke up her cloaths, and bared her before her mother ſaying, he would ſee whether ſhe had any <hi>pubes</hi> upon her or no; and in many places the like barbarous demeanour had bin uſed: at which the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hearing her daughter ſcreech out, and ſeeing how in vaine ſhe ſtruggled againſt him, being therewith grievouſly offended, ſhe cryed out alſo, and leaving the houſe run into the ſtreet amongſt her Neighbours, clamoring about that there was one within that would raviſh her daughter<hi>:</hi> The noyſe and hubbub grew ſuddenly ſo great, that it came to the eare of the Husband, who was then tyling of an houſe in the Town; who inſtantly ſnatching up his Lathing-ſtaffe made what haſt he could
<pb facs="tcp:156461:3"/> home, where finding his daughter weeping and perceiving how ſhe had bin ruffled by the Collector, demanded of him the reaſon of his vncivill boldneſſe? who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him he was a ſawcy fellow to aske him ſuch a queſtion, hee had authority for what he did, neither would be give him any account at all for what had paſſed; and withall made offer to ſtrike at the Tyler, who avoyding the blow up with his ſtaffe, and reached him ſuch a knock upon the pate that he brake his Skull, and the braines flew about the roome, which ſeeing he preſently left the houſe, told the Neighbours what had hapned, that his cauſe was now theirs, at which there was great noyſe and uproare, they all juſtifying the act to be good and honeſt, and that to their beſt and utmoſt power, with their lives and goods, they would aſſiſt and ſupport him.</p>
            <p>And thus that many-headed monſter, the multitude being drawne together, they tumultuouſly went from thence unto Maid-ſtone, and from thence increaſing their number, they came back to Black Heath, incouraging all the Country as they paſt along, to be partakers with them in their commotion, when beſetting all the waies that directed either from London to Canterbury, or from thence to London: They ſtaid and arreſted all Paſſengers of what degree or condition foever, compelling them to ſweare; Firſt that they ſhould keep faſt and firme their Allegeance to the good King <hi>Richard,</hi> and to the Commons, and next, if his Majeſty ſhould faile, they ſhould accept of no Soveraigne whoſe name was <hi>Iohn,</hi> which was for the great envy which they bare unto <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of
<hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and uncle to the King, who by reaſon of his conqueſt of Spaine, writ himſelfe King of Caſtile. And further that they ſhould not yeeld unto any Taxe that ſhould be leavied in the Kingdome, from thence forward, nor conſent unto any unleſſe it were a fifteene.</p>
            <p>The rumor of theſe bold and preſumptuous actions, was quickly ſpread into Suſſex, Eſſex, Hertford-ſhire, Cambridge-ſhire, Suffolke, Norfolke &amp;c. for <hi>Fama malum quo non aliud velocius—</hi>now when theſe daily conventions of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons increaſed, and their number was almoſt growne unto an infinite, ſo that they thought themſelves to be of that ſtrength, that no power was able to reſiſt them; they began now to thinke of nothing but miſdemeanour and misbeliefe, framing themſelves to all the rebellious irregularity that could be deviſed even unto brutiſh cruelty.</p>
            <p>For firſt they proclaimed an Edict, to apprehend all Lawyers, whether Judges, Benchers, Barriſters or younger Students, and all Juſtices of Peace, or grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and to cut off their heads, of which they ſpared none that fell into their hands, neither was there any one, whom they ſuppoſed to have any learning at all, if they found but a Pen and Inkhorne about him, upon whom they did not unanimouſly cry out with this acclamation,
<hi>Hence away with him, cut off his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rebells of Eſſex having joyned themſelves with theſe of <hi>Kent,</hi> there came certaine Noble men, and Knights from the King to them, being then on black Heath, to demand of them the cauſe of this their unlawfull aſſembly, to whom they ſawcily and moſt unreverently made anſwer: That for certaine cauſes beſt known <pb facs="tcp:156461:3"/> to themſelves they were come together: but the chiefeſt was to have ſome talke with the King, and therefore bad them tell him ſo, and further if hee would come thither in perſon, they would tell him their grievances, but to none elſe they would reveale them.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty by ſome who was neare about him was counſelled becauſe of the preſent neceſsity to ſatisfie their requeſt in that, and by reaſon it was no further to give unto them a meeting with all ſpeed poſsible; but <hi>Symon Sudbury</hi> then Arch-Biſhop of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Lord Chancellor, and <hi>Robert Hales,</hi> of St.
<hi>Iohns,</hi> Lord high Treaſure would by no meanes admit of their Counſell, affirming that it was not for the Kings honour to yeeld to the deſires of ſuch baſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory Rebells: but rather to take order for the ſpeedy leavying of an Army to ſuppreſſe them: of which the Commons having got Intelligence<hi>:</hi> they ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vowed, and in great furie ſwore, that they would cut off thoſe Traytors heads, and to that purpoſe, they left black Heath, and inſtantly marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt they diſperſed themſelves in Southwarke, filling all the places of the Barrough, and the place being not able to containe a tenth part of them, they quartered themſelves in the fields, and Countrey thereabouts; and by reaſon of the vow'd malice and envy that they bore unto the Arch-Biſhop, their firſt Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous attempt was to ſet upon his Pallace at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> which they rifled and ſpoyled, and wonder it was, in regard of their Brutiſh furie, that they had not ſet it on fire, and burnt it downe to the ground.</p>
            <p>In the interim, the Lord Major, and the Aldermen, fearing alſo that they would make ſpoyle of the City, called a Counſell amongſt themſelves, in which many things were debated for their publick ſecurity, and in the end concluded to ſhut up their gates, let downe their Percullices, chained their ſtreets, and the Citizens ſhould arme themſelves, man the wals, and ſtand upon their guard. But the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks and meaneſt ſort of people, who alwayes are apt to envie their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and are therefore prone to any Innovation, favouring the cauſe of the ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Commons, were ſo farre from ſuffering the Major and the Sheriffes to come neare unto the gates, and by ſhutting them to keep the Rebells out, that they inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently oppoſed them, threatning death to any ſhould attempt it.</p>
            <p>This was the occaſion, that all the night following being the Eve before <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti</hi> day, the Rebells had free ingreſſe and egreſſe in and out of the gates, by which they ſtirred up the Commons of the City, as Artificers, Labourers, and Apprentiſes to take part with them, and joyne to their faction, making a faire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that their purpoſe was onely to ſearch out ſuch as were traytors to the King and his Realme, and they being cut off, to make a ceſſation of Armes, and every one peaceably to retyre himſelfe into his owne Country.</p>
            <p>This faire pretence wrought much in the hearts of the giddy multitude, and the rather becauſe notwithſtanding their great number, which was difficultly to be guided they offered violence neither to man nor woman neither tooke any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity from them, but at a juſt and competent price; for whomſoever of their <pb facs="tcp:156461:4"/> owne ſociety they found either pillidging or ſtealing, they uſed Martiall Law, and commanded his head inſtantly to be ſmitten off: The morrow after they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with divers of the moſt ſubſtantiall Commons of the City to whom if they would adhere unto them, and take part with them, they promiſed abſolute freedome and liberty: inſomuch that the moſt or all of the meaner ſort, were ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely drawne into their conſpiracie<hi>:</hi> for joy whereof they were admitted into the Vintners and Merchants Cellers, where they quaffed and dranke together Healths by no allowance, with which Licence not being acquainted, it ſo wrought within them, that ſome were merry, others mad: a motion was made to goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to the <hi>Savoy,</hi> which then was the Pallace, and domeſtick dwelling of the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> a place for the rich furniture thereto belonging, through the whole Kingdome was not to be paralleld) and either to burne it, or raze it downe to the earth; for he being an excellent and worthy Prince, their malice towards him was implacable.</p>
            <p>Thither they tumultuouſly hurried in heapes, and ſetting fire in diverſe places thereof made it ſuddenly all in a flame, and to give the greater coour to their inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, cauſed Proclamation to be made, that that was done was not to their owne uſe or proper ends, for no man upon paine of death ſhould reſerve any thing, but that all plate and veſſells of Silver and gold, or jewells which were there in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance ſhould be battered, defaced, and broken into ſmall peeces and caſt into the river, which was accordingly performed, but as our Author writeth, one of the Rebells contrary to the Proclamation tooke a ſilver Plate, and hid it in his boſome, which being eſpyed by one of his fellow Raſcalls, hee made it knowne to the reſt, who inſtantly laid hold upon him, and without further examination or Triall, caſt him into the fire with the Plate, with this loude acclamation, <hi>Wee are the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Truth and juſtiec and are neither Theeves nor robbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is further remarkable, that ſome of theſe robbers, to the number of two or three and thirty had got into a Celler of the ſame houſe, where they dranke ſo much ſweet and pleaſant wine, that they could not find the way out againe in any ſeaſonable time, but with the ruines of the houſe were ſo barracadoed in with Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, rubbiſh and ſtone, that they were heard crying and calling for helpe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour ſeaven dayes after, where they periſht, all being or not able, or not willing to releive them.</p>
            <p>This exploit being over, they againe aſſembled and broke open a place which was cald the new Temple at the barre, which was a place for Lawyers, and quite demoliſht it for no other reaſon, but the hate which they bore to Sr, <hi>Robert Hayles,</hi> Maſter of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Hoſpitall, unto which place that of St. <hi>Iohns</hi> of the Temple belonged. There many writings and Monuments which were then in the cuſtody of the Lawyers were deſtroyed by fire<hi>:</hi> after the ruine of this place, many through wearineſſe, and others over-laded with wine, lay downe under the walls and ſtalls there a bouts, where ſome were ſlaine by thoſe on whom they had committed ſuch out-rages, and ſome kild one another upon that advantage for antient and former grudges.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:156461:4"/> In the interim whilſt theſe things were in action, another dangerou troop had gathered themſelves together to ſet fire on the Pallace of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> in <hi>Clarkenwell,</hi> which was ſeene to burne ſeven dayes together, they not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering any man to lay a helping hand to quench it, on the Friday after they burnt the mannor of
<hi>Highbury,</hi> the multitude of the Commons being at that time divided into three ſeverall bands, of which diviſion one part was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the burning of <hi>Highbury</hi> and other places belonging to the Prior of St.
<hi>Iohns.</hi> A ſecond Company lay at <hi>Mile-End</hi> Eaſt of the City, A third lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves upon the Tower-hill, to intercept all ſuch Victuall as was for the Kings proviſion, whilſt they on <hi>Mile-end</hi> ſent a bold and perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meſſage to the King to make his perſonall appearance before them, and that too all delays and excuſes ſet apart unarmed, and without any guard or power to attend him, which if he ſhould deny to doe, they would not onely pluck downe the Tower upon his head, but neither he, nor any of his Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants ſhould depart alive. Obſerve herein what rebellion is, and to what impudence it growes, when thoſe that are the Actors therein tranſgreſſe all the bounds of Religion and reaſon, but it followeth (for ſo the Chronicle relates) that his Majeſty adviſed by ſome few that were at that time about him, with a ſmall traine, and thoſe altogether unarmed went towards them, (no doubt in great feare) riding on horſeback. The gates of the Tower ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding open, and a great many of the raſcall rabble entring and returning at their owne wills and pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Here is another thing worthy of note to all Poſterity, but eſpecially to the braver ſpirits of our own Nation, that there were at the ſame inſtant, ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Armed men reputed valiant and expert in Armes, beſides ſixe hundred able Archers, who all this time hanging down their heads, were mute and ſtood amazed. They being appointed to guard the ſacred perſon of the King who ſuffered thoſe peſantly ruſticks void of all manners or humanity to enter his Highneſſe privy Bed-chamber, and the Queene <hi>Dowager</hi> his mothers, with their weapons in their hands, and yet againſt them, made at all no reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance N<hi>:</hi> ay ſaw them there to play the impudent wantons by lying and ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on his Highneſſe owne bed, and further in their homely and baſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couterment, moſt ſawcily to offer to ruffle and kiſſe the mother queen, whilſt they ſtood patiently by &amp; ſufred it, had theſe things bin reported to have bin done in any other Forraigne Countres, as we ſhould have thought them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether incredible, but they are related by our owne Domoſtick Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were in agitation, ſome of this rude rabble made ſtrict inquiry for the Arch-biſhop, and ſome ſearching one place, and ſome another, and not finding him, at length finding one of his ſervants, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible fury they threatned unto him preſent death, unleſſe he would bring them to his Lord and Maſter, whom they moſt unreverently called by their owne name Rebel and traytor.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:156461:5"/> This groome fearing his life, and therefore not any way daring to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict or to diſpleaſe them, preſently conducted them to the Chappell in the Kings Lodgings, where after maſſe had beene ſaid and ſang, the Reverent Prelate was then buſie in his private Oriſons, for having received the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ignorant either of their comming or purpoſe, he had the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore confeſt himſelfe to his Ghoſtly Father (for ſuch was the cuſtome in thoſe dayes) who when he heard that they were come, and had broke open ſome doores againſt him, with a noble and Chriſtian-like conſtancy ſaid to thoſe few of his retinew who at that time attended him. The enemie is now come, let us goe and boldly meete him, for ſeeing things ſtand as they now doe, it is much better for us to dye like Martyrs, then to live, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported no better then Malefactors.</p>
            <p>At which word the Rebels entred with this clamor, where is this Traytor to the King and common-wealth? To which he anſwered, Loe I am the man you ſeeke, the Arch-biſhop but no Traytor, where preſently they laid rude and violent hands upon his Sacred perſon, and dragging him out of the Chappell, drew him from the Tower, to the Tower hill, where being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed and incloſed with their ſwords and weapons advanced, he appeared no way diſcouraged or daunted, but with a Martyr-like conſtancy uttered theſe words following.</p>
            <p>Reſolve me, my deare brethren, what you purpoſe to doe, what is my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt you or any man for which you purpoſe to ſhed mine innocent blood, it were good for you to adviſe before you take away my life, for if I be thus undeſervedly ſlaine, who am your Paſtor, there muſt conſequently fall upon you, the great indignation of the juſt Revenger, beſides for ſuch an heinous fact, all the whole ſhall be interdicted: ſcarce had he ended thoſe few words before they cryed out with an horrible clamour that the men there feared nor cared for any interdiction, nor would they allow the Pope to have any power or Supremacy over them: the Archbiſhop ſeeing his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable death before him (being an eloquent man, and wiſe, beyond moſt of the Kingdome) gave unto them very faire and comfortable words, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring them only to give ſome ſhort ſpace to pray for his ſoules health, and then he would ſubmit himſelfe to their utmoſt cruelty, which being ſcarcely granted, hee forgave the Executioner and kneeling downe offered his head to be ſmitten off by the headſman.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſtroke made a great wound in his neck, but was not mortall, when the Arch-biſhop putting his hand to the place uttered theſe words, Aha, it is the hand of God, nor could he ſo ſoone remove his hand but at the ſecond blow he wounded him deeper and cut off the ends of his fingers, at which he fell groveling, but was ſtill alive, till being piteouſly mangled by eight ſeverall blowes he gave up his laſt breath into his hands from whom he firſt received it, all that day his body lay unburied, and till the morrow being <hi>Satterday</hi> none daring to affoord it at any buriall, but tooke his head <pb facs="tcp:156461:5"/> and nayling his head upon it fixt it on a Pole, and ſet it upon London Bridge in the ſame place where before was fixt the head of Sir <hi>Iohn Minſter-worth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This reverend Arch Biſhop <hi>Simon Tibald,</hi> Alias
<hi>Sandbury,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Nicholas Tibald</hi> borne in Sudbury, a towne in Norfolk, Doctor of both Lawes, had beene eighteene yeares Biſhop of London, who was cruelly murthered, and his body af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter borne to Canterbury, and buried in the Cathedrall Church: There dyed with him a moſt valiant Knight called Sir <hi>Robert Hayles,</hi> Lord of St. <hi>Iohns,</hi> and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of England with <hi>Iohn Legat,</hi> one of the Kings Sergeants at Armes, and with them a Fryer of the Order of St. <hi>Frances,</hi> whoſe name was
<hi>William Axpledore,</hi> and was at that time Confeſſor to the King. There was executed alſo by the Brutiſh tyranny of theſe Rebells, one
<hi>Richard Lyons,</hi> an exquiſite Lapidary, and a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, who had bin ſome few yeares before Shriefe of the City of London, who was moſt inhumainly drawne out of his owne houſe into Cheape ſide, and there beheaded.</p>
            <p>Many the ſame day had their heads cut off, as well Flemings as Engliſh and for no other cauſe, but onely to fulfill the madneſſe of the barbarous Commons, for they ſpared no men who were not of their diabolcall faction, but they cut off their heads, ſaying, they cared not whether they ſent them, to God, or to the Divell: All ſacred places they hold in contempt, as ſuch as they had never bin acquainted with, for even in the Temples, and at the time of divine Service, they did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to kill and murder any man to whom they had any ſpleene or malice: But eſpecially their envy was to the Dutch, whom they termed by the generall name of Flemings, who as they ſuppoſed ſucked the very moyſture and marrow of the Kingdome, and therefore out of the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Fryers Church in London, they fetched thirteene Flemings, and out of another Church, (not named in the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle) to the number of ſeventeene, and thirty two out of the Vine-tree, and ſo out of other places of the City, as alſo Southwarke, whoſe heads they ſtruck off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mercy, unleſſe they could plainely pronounce Breed and Cheeſe, for if their ſpeech ſounded any way towards <hi>Brott</hi> and <hi>Cawſe,</hi> off went their heads without redemption, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But I leſt the King at Mile-end, it is moſt pertinent to the Hiſtory that I give you account how he ſped there; thus therefore it followeth: His Majeſty riding the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rather commanded then invited, was in a great ſtraite and feare withall, when he caſt his eye upon ſuch a multitude of unruly Raſcalls, who with ſupercilious fronts gave him an unmannerly ſalute, he there from faſhioned himſelfe to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of preſent and demanded of them what they deſired? who delivered unto him a writing, which they ſaid they would have him confirme by his Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, the effect of part of their demands were theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that all men in the Kingdome whatſoever, ſhould be free from ſervitude and bondage, ſo as from that time there ſhould be no bond-men at all, or to hold any Tenure in villanage &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that he ſhould grant his free and generall pardon to all men of what eſtate ſoever, of all manner of Actions, or inſurrections committed, and all Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, <pb facs="tcp:156461:6"/> Treaſon, Fellonics, Extortions, Robberies, traingreſſions by any of them done, and further that their peace might bee ſo confirmed, that there-after their former inſolencies might not be called in queſtion, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that all perſons from time forward might be infranchiſed, and have free liberty to buy and ſell in every Country, City, Borrough Towne, Fayre, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket or otherwiſe within the Realm of England, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that no Acres of Land held in ſervice or bondage, ſhould bee held but for ſome pence the Acre, and if it had gone for leſſe in former time, it ſhould not there-after be inhanced: Theſe and many other things they required, to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by his Majeſty, telling him boldly withall, that he had evilly governed till that day, and that they would take order that from that time forward be ſhould be better counſelled.</p>
            <p>The King perceiving by their ſudden foure countenances, that unleſſe he granted punctually to every of their demands, (though never ſo unreaſonable) his perſon was in great danger, being by them round mvironed, and therefore no poſſible meanes of his eſcape ſealed to their writings; and deſiring Truce for ſome ſmall time departed thence without any violence done unto his perſon; and the Eſſex men returned home peaceably into their Country.</p>
            <p>On the morrow being Satterday, and the fifteenth or June, the King after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, went from the Ward-robe in the Royall which is in London, to Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to viſite the ſhrine of St. <hi>Edward</hi> King and Confeſſor, and withall to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon it they had committed any out-rage by defacing it: Then went he to the Chappell called our Lady in the Piew, where after he had offered up his Oriſons he returned by the Suburbs of Weſt Smith-field, where he found the place thronged with the Kentiſh Rebells, wherefore he ſent to their Captaine to informe them, that he had pacified their fellowes the Eſſex men, who had abandoned Mile-end, and were peaceably departed home-ward, and that he was pleaſed in his gracious clemency to grant unto them the like conditions of peace; and ſuperſcribe to the ſame Articles if they pleaſed to accept of them.</p>
            <p>But their chiefe Captaine whom ſome call <hi>Iohn,</hi> but the beſt Chronologers call <hi>Walter Hiliard,</hi> Alias <hi>Tyler,</hi> being of a ſubtle and crafty condition, and wickedly witty made anſwer, that though he had then the power in his hands, yet hee was willing to liſten unto peace but onely thus, with ſome particular conditions added to his owne approbation and liking, his purpoſe being to feed the King and the Nobility with delayes, till hee had compaſſed his diabolicall purpoſe, whoſe plot was firſt the ſame night to have ſurpriſed the King, and all thoſe Peeres which then attended him, Courtiers and others, and then to have ſpoyled the City, and then to have burnt it to the earth, by ſetting fire in foure parts thereof at once.</p>
            <p>But the Providence of Heaven, who alwaies favoureth and protecteth Juſtice and innocenſe, diverted his miſchiefe which he intended againſt others, &amp; powred it on his owne head, as ſhall appeare by the ſequell. For whereas the conditions of peace were ingroſſed in their ſeverall Charters, and thrice ſent unto him by the King not any of them ſeemed to pleaſe him, therefore his Majeſty ſent unto him a <pb facs="tcp:156461:6"/> Knight, Sir <hi>Iohn Newton,</hi> a man both of great courage and diſcretion not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but to entreat him, as from the King his Soveraigne (for his great inſolence and pride was knowne to all) that hee would vouchſafe to come and ſpeake with him about his owne demands, which ſhould be inſerted into his Charter: of which demands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by this one which I will ſet downe, it may manifeſtly appeare, how uncharit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble how unchriſtianlike all the reſt were.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he deſired to have a Commiſſion ſealed, to behead all Lawyers, of what degree ſoever, from the higheſt to the loweſt; all Eſcheaters, or whatſoever by reaſon of their office communicated with the Law. For his apprehenſion was, and if this could be compaſſed, all affaires ſhould be ordered according to the fancie of the Commons, and to change the Monarchy into an Anarchy: For (it is ſaid) that but the day before he had made his boaſt, putting his hand to his lips that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore foure dayes were come about, all the Lawes of England ſhould proceed from his owne mouth.</p>
            <p>Now whilſt the Knight importuned him for diſpatch, that he might returne his anſwer to the King his Maſter, he contracted his brow, and in great rage replyed: <hi>If thou beeſt ſo haſtie, go get thee back unto him, and ſay; I will come unto him at mine owne pleaſure and leiſure.</hi> Notwithſtanding which, hee followed on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back with a ſtately and ſlow pace, caſting his eyes about him (as he rode) as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in the multitude, and that he had been the Prince of all that people. In his way hee was encountred by a Doublet-maker, who had delivered in threeſcore doublets to the chiefe of the Commons by his appointment and demanded for them thirtie marks, to whom the Captaine made anſwer; <hi>Friend content thy ſelfe for a while, I will ſee thee well and fully ſatisfied before this day be fully ended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He then ſet forward, leaving his company behind'him, and came ſo neare unto the King, that his horſe bruſhed againſt the Kings horſes crupper, and the firſt words hee ſpake unto him were theſe;
<hi>Sir King, ſeeſt thou all you people? Yes,</hi> anſwered the <hi>but whereſore doeſt thou ask me that queſtion? Becauſe</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed he)
<hi>they be all at my commandement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and have ſworne to me their faith and obedience, to do all things what ſoever I ſhall impoſe on them. In good time,</hi> anſwered the King, <hi>I beleeve it well.</hi> Then ſaid the Rebell, <hi>Beleeveſt thou King, that this people, and as many mo as be in this Citie at my command and ſervice, will depart from thee thus without thy Charters? No,</hi> ſaid the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>you ſhall willingly receive them, and they ſhall be preſently delivered unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Soldiers armed with pikes look on as Sir William Walworth, Lord Mayor of London, strikes Wat Tyler on the head with a ceremonial mace. Commoners, armed with pitchforks, walk away.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>In this Interim the Lord Mayor, for his laſt noble and memorable enterpriſe, worthy to be eternized, to ſecond his former pecce of ſervice, ſped him inſtantly into the City, and cryed out aloud; You good and faithfull Citizens, arme your ſelves with all ſpeed poſſible, and helpe to aſſiſt your King and Soveraigne, who is in grear perill to be ſlaine; and ayde me your Major and Governour who am in the danger, or if you will not ſuffer me, yet leave not his ſelect Majeſty deſtitute.</p>
            <p>Which when the well-minded Cityzens heard in whoſe loyall breſt the love of their King was ingraven, they preſently to the number of a thouſand armed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſtaid in the ſtreets attending for ſome Captaine to order them, and leade them towards the King, at which inſtant came to them a noble Knight and a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, who was alſo a freeman of the City: him they intreated to take upon him that charge, to which he willingly and moſt cheerefully aſſented, the greateſt part of them were under his conduct, the reſt were commanded by the Lord Major, one
<hi>Preducus Dalbret,</hi> and ſome other Knight in the ſtory not named. Theſe with this ayde preſented themſelves before the King, who greatly rejoycing in the faith and loyalty of his armed Citizens, preſently with theſe freſh forces compaſſed the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells about.</p>
            <p>Now there appeared (by Gods wonderfull goodnes) a ſudden and unexpected alteration, for the ſeditious Commons who but ſome few minutes before ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch peremptory and proud tearmes with the King himſelfe, finding themſelves thus invironed, flung downe their weapons at once, and with a loud unanimous voyce cryed pardon, pardon; ſuch as could eſcape out of the Ring fled, and hid themſelves, ſome in Cellers, others in the Corne fields, Woods and Ditches, &amp;c. They being now at the Kings mercy, the Lords and the reſt about deſirous to take ſome vengeance of their former inſolency, beſought his Majeſty that for example ſake he would command ſome hundred or two of their heads to bee ſtrunk off, to whoſe requeſt he would no way condeſcend, but gave order that their Charter which was ſealed ſhould be delivered unto them, which was to prevent a new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as knowing, that Eſſex was not yet altogether pacified nor Kent quieted. <pb facs="tcp:156461:8"/> The Commons having gotten their Charter, and much taken with the Kings extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and unexpected mercy, they left both City and Suburbs, and departed homeward; when the King calling the Lord Major before him he Knighted him in the Field, as he had moſt worthily deſerved: The like he did to <hi>Nicholas Brember, Iohn Philpot, Robert Lawnd, Iohn Standiſh, Nicholas Twiſord,</hi> and <hi>Adam Frances</hi> Aldermen, and after entred the City in great ſtate, where he was joyfully received from thence, he went to viſite his Mother, who was at that time lodged in the Tower Royall, in a part thereof called the Queenes Wardrope, where ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained for the ſpace of two dayes and two nights, the time of this combuſtion, much bewayling and lamenting her Sons imminent danger, whom when ſhe ſaw to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ſafe ſhe was greatly comforted, and with teares of joy ſaid: <hi>O my deare Son, what ſorrowes have I ſuffered for you even to this houre?</hi> who anſwered againe, <hi>Certainly Madam, I knew it well but now rejoyce, and praiſe God with me, for I have this day recovered mine Heritage, and the Realm of England, which I had almoſt loſt: Then he gave preſent Commandements, that the Arch-Biſhops head ſhould be taken from off the Bridge, and</hi> Wat Tylers <hi>to be ſet in the place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty further in remembrance of this joyfull day, and for the Cities greater honour, who next under God were his ſole deliverers granted, that in regard that worthy <hi>William Walworth</hi> the Lord Major had ſtaine that dangerous Rebell with a Dagger, a bloudy Dagger ſhould therefore be added unto the Armes of the City, and to be placed in the right quarter of the Eſcutchion as an addition to the Armes, and to celebrate the memory of a Lord Majors valiant act, for before that time the City bore onely a Croſſe without a Dagger.</p>
            <p>And where it hath bin vulgarly bruted, that the Rebell whom Sir
<hi>William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> flew was not <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> but <hi>Iack Straw,</hi> that doubt is thus eaſily reconcil'd; for <hi>Iack Straw</hi> was not taken till after the death of <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> being then appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended with divers others the chiefe of that horrible ſedition, who being brought into the Guild-hall where the Lord Major ſate in Judgement, having pronounced the Sentence of death upon them; he openly ſpake to <hi>Iack Straw</hi> as followeth:</p>
            <p>John behold thy Sentence is paſt, and thine unavoidable death at hand, for thou haſt not many houres to live; wherefore I intreat thee, ſince there is no way to ſave thy body, that for thy ſoules health thou wilt now without extenuating thy grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous fault which is inexcuſable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that thou betwixt God and thy Conſcience reſolve this Honourable Bench, what the utmoſt of your purpoſe was, and to what end you ſo mutinouſly aſſembled the Commons: who making a ſad pauſe to this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, The Lord Major againe thus ſeconded it; I ſpeake to thee as to a dying man, who now ought to ſtudy for the peace of thy ſoule, and not diſſemble at all either with God, or man: at which words recollecting his ſpirits, hee returned this anſwer following:</p>
            <p>Now I confeſſe in vaine it booteth me not either to lye, or make any delatory or evaſive excuſe, underſtanding that if I ſhould ſo doe, I might indanger my ſoule unto the greater torments; and beſides, I hope to obtaine two benefits by ſpeaki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g truth: Firſt, that I thereby may ſomewhat benefit the Common-weale in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <pb facs="tcp:156461:8"/> and next according to your promiſes, I hope to bee aſſiſted by your prayers, that God would be mercifull unto my ſoule. And therefore thus I deliver unto you my conſcience faithfully, and without deceite.</p>
            <p>Being aſſembled upon blacke Heath, at that time when we ſent for the King to come unto us, our reſolution was, to have ſlaine all the Nobles, Knights, and Eſquires about him, and to have taken him into our own cuſtody, to the intent that the people might have repayred unto us with more boldneſſe, and leſſe feare; ſince we would have made them to beleeve, that whatſoever we did was by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Authority: And next when we had got ſuch power that we needed not to be affraid of any other forces which might be raiſed in the Kingdome, our purpoſe was then to have ſlaine all ſuch of the Nobility, as might either have given Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, or made any reſiſtance againſt us. But more in particular, wee would have maſſacred all the Knights of the <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and St. <hi>Iohns</hi> Knights, or burned their houſes over their eares: And laſtly, we would have ſlaine the King himſelfe, and all Gentlemen of any revenue throughout the Kingdome, with all Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Monks, Canons, and Parſons of Churches, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving onely ſome few Mendicants or begging Fryers, they being ſufficiently able for ſaying Maſſe, and the adminiſtration of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>And having made a cleare riddance of all thoſe unneceſſary Members of the Common-weale (for ſo at that time it pleaſed us to call them) wee would have abrogated the old Lawes, and deviſed new according to our own fancies; by which the whole Realm ſhould be governed, for we had determined to have divided the Kingdome, and to have made Kings amongſt our ſelves, as <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> in Kent, my ſelfe in Eſſex, and others in other places: but by reaſon that theſe our deſignes were prevented by the Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury, who diſſwaded the King from comming amongſt us, we vowed by all meanes to inſidiate his life, and to diſpatch him out of the way, which we did after: And further, the ſelf ſame evening that
<hi>Wat Tyler</hi> was ſlaine in Smithfield, we reſolutely determined, (having the greateſt part of the Commons of the City bent to aſſiſt us in the Act) to ſet fire in foure ſeverall parts of the ſame at once, and to have divided the ſpoile amongſt us: and this ſaith he, was our reſolved purpoſe, and concluded on by all, as God may helpe me now at my laſt end. After this Confeſſion made, he with many others of his late faction, were lead unto the place of Execution, whoſe heads being ſtruck off, his was put upon a pole and ſet upon the Bridge next unto <hi>Wat Tylers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I might enter into a large diſcourſe of the horridneſſe of Rebellion; as that of Ireland, whoſe diſtreſſed eſtate is very lamentable, whoſe rebellion and outrages I hope will be conſidered, and they ſpeedily (by the permiſſion of the Almighty) receive their juſt rewards. Rebellion can no way be better illuſtrated then by the ſad and lamentable effects expreſſed in the premiſſes: I will therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with that of the Prophet <hi>Samuel, Rebellion is as the ſin of Witchcraft, and Tranſgreſſion is wickednes and Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="Jack Straw" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:156461:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Ghoſt of</hi> Iack Straw.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> That did Act on Smithfields bloudy ſtage,</l>
               <l>In ſecond <hi>Richards</hi> young and tender age;</l>
               <l>And there receiv'd from <hi>Walworths</hi> fatall hand</l>
               <l>The ſtab of death, which life did countermand;</l>
               <l>And made an equall to the Tragedy</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Leyden,</hi> a Dutch Taylors villany:</l>
               <l>Not that I ere conſorted with that ſlave,</l>
               <l>My Raſcall rout you in this Story have:</l>
               <l>But that in name and nature we agree,</l>
               <l>An Engliſh Taylor I, Dutch Rebell he;</l>
               <l>In my <hi>Conſort,</hi> I had the Prieſt <hi>Iohn Ball,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mynter</hi> the Clerke, unto his ſhare did fall.</l>
               <l>He, to have all things common did intend,</l>
               <l>And my Rebellion was to ſuch an end:</l>
               <l>Even in a word, we both were like appointed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>To take away the ſword from Gods Annoynted;</l>
               <l>And for examples to the Worlds laſt day,</l>
               <l>Our Traytors name ſhall never weare away;</l>
               <l>The fearefull paths that he and I have trod,</l>
               <l>Have bin accurſed in the ſight of God.</l>
               <l>Here in this Regiſter, who ere doth looke</l>
               <l>(Which may be rightly call'd <hi>The Bloudy Booke)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall ſee how baſe and rude theſe villaines be,</l>
               <l>That doe attempt like <hi>Leyden,</hi> plot like me:</l>
               <l>And now the Divell in whoſe name they're gone,</l>
               <l>Payes them Hells wages, when their worke is done;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Treaſon</hi> is bloudy, bloud thereon attends,</l>
               <l>Traytors are bloudy, and have bloudy ends.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Meaning the Iriſh Rebels.</note> To you, my brother Rebells in like kind,</l>
               <l>That doe uſurpe authority, you'l find</l>
               <l>The ſame reward which we ſhall feele too ſoone,</l>
               <l>A horrid Conſcience at the day of Doome:</l>
               <l>Which to avoyd let this my Ghoſt intreat,</l>
               <l>Yes love your King, feare Heavens Tribunall Seat;</l>
               <l>So ſhall your ſoules without diſturbance rest,</l>
               <l>Till Chriſt ſhall come to make you fully bleſt.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
